主演：简 玛奇
梁 家 辉
情  人
翻译：舒杭生
北平℡英文翻译工作室
hsheng06@gmail.com
改编自玛格丽特 杜拉斯的小说
情窦初开时 我误入歧途
Very early in my life,it was too late.
到我十八岁时 过失已无法挽回
At 18, it was already too late.
十八岁那年 我老了
At 18, I aged.
这衰老是残酷的
This aging was brutal.
我看着它爬上我的面胧
This aging, I saw it spread over my features ...
一点儿一点儿
one by one.
我非但没有为此恐惧
Instead of being frightened by it ...
反倒望着我的脸日渐衰老
I saw this aging of my face ...
象是在读一本书
with the same sort of interest I might have taken, for example...
津津有味
in the reading of a book.
我保留了那张新的面孔
That new face, I kept it.
面部的线条没有改变
It's kept the same contours ...
但内涵毁掉了
but its matter is destroyed.
我的脸是一张毁掉的脸
I have a destroyed face.
请允许我再讲一遍这段往事
Let me tell you again.
我还不到十六岁
I'm 15 1/2.
在湄公河的一条渡船上
It's the crossing of a ferry on the Mekong.
看看我那时候的样子吧
Look at me.
我还不到十六岁
I'm 15 1/2.
正准备渡河
It's the crossing of the river.
返回西贡
When I go back to Saigon ...
象是在旅行一样 ...
it's as though I'm on a journey ...
尤其是在我乘巴士的时候
especially when I take the bus.
那是暑假后返校的日子
That day, it's the end of the school holidays.
我不记得是哪次暑假了
I don't remember which one.
我去了沙沥市  和我的两个兄弟一起度假
I went to spend it in Sa-Dec with my two brothers ...
挤在妈妈的小房子里 ...
in my mother's tight house ...
沙 沥 小 学
在沙沥小学的后面
behind the bush school ...
家里每天充满恐怖的气氛
in the horror of the Sa-Dec house.
大块的是我的
The big pieces are mine.
为什么是你的？
Why yours?
因为这是规矩
Because that's the way it is.
你去死好了！
I wish you'd die.
保罗？
Paul?
Paulo?
保罗 回来睡觉吧
Paul, come to bed.
你什么都不用怕了
You mustn't be afraid anymore:
不用怕皮埃尔  什么都不用怕
not of Pierre, not of anything.
再也不用怕了
Never again, you know.
Never again.
他回来了？
He came back?
我看到他在阳台 ...
I see him on the balcony ...
在外面过夜
sleeping in the night outside ...
不想回房间
doesn't want to go to his room.
他太怕皮埃尔了
He's too scared of Pierre.
我  我是担心他在外面过夜
Me, it's when he's outside that I'm afraid.
担心他离家出走
I'm afraid he'll leave like that.
他会迷路的
He'll get lost.
这样的孩子很容易迷路
It can happen with that kind of child.
你说得不对！
That's not true.
你才不担心保罗！
You're not afraid for Paul.
你只担心皮埃尔
You're only afraid for Pierre.
你为什么这么爱他 ...
Why is it that you love him so much ...
却从来不爱我们俩？
and not us ...never?
我爱你们三个孩子 一视同仁
I love all three of my children the same.
你说得不对  不对！
That's not true. It's not true!
回答我 你为什么这么爱他 ...
Answer! Why is it that you love him so much ...
却不爱我们俩？
and not us?
我不知道为什么
I don't know why.
昨天 ...
Yesterday ...
我写信给西贡 ...
I wrote to Saigon ...
要他们遣返皮埃尔
to ask for Pierre's repatriation.
什么？
What?
我要把他送回法国
I'm sending him back to France.
你高兴了吧？
You're happy?
他又去烟馆偷鸦片了
He stole at the opium den again.
我再没钱付给人家了
I can't pay any longer.
该结束了
It's over.
不能再这样下去了
It's not possible anymore.
沙 沥 小 学
妈 赶快  要发车了
Mom, hurry up, or I'll miss the bus.
沙沥－永隆－西贡
拜 保罗
Bye, Paulo.
路上小心
Take care.
懂了  妈
Yes, Mom.
你什么时候回来？
When are you coming back?
狂欢节的时候  我跟你说过
For Mardi Gras. I already told you.
噢  我忘了
Oh. I forgot.
西贡\143公里
就这样 我在那天返回西贡
So that day I'm going back to Saigon.
我穿着我的舞鞋 戴着我的男士帽
I'm wearing my cabaret shoes and my man's hat.
那时候整个殖民地没有一个女人 没有一个年轻姑娘
No woman, no young girl wears a man's fedora ...
戴男士礼帽
in that colony in those days.
本地女人也不戴
No native woman, either.
那顶帽子我从不离身
That hat, I never leave it.
它是属于我的 － 这顶帽子
I have that, this hat.
只要有了它 我就是完整的
That all by itself makes me whole.
没有它 我永远不是完整的
I'm never without it.
于是 我乘坐永隆和沙沥之间的渡船
So it's the crossing ...
横渡湄公河的一条支流
of one of the branches of the Mekong on the ferry that's between Vinh Long and Sa-Dec
这里被称为印度支那南部的
in the great plains of mud and rice ...
泥巴和稻米大平原
of southern Indochina ...
鸟之川
the plain of the birds.
打扰了 小姐  您抽烟吗？
Excuse me, mademoiselle. Do you smoke?
不抽 谢谢
No, thank you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
一位年轻的白人姑娘乘坐土著人的巴士
It's so surprising ...
实在令人吃惊
a young white girl on a native bus.
我喜欢您的帽子  很有创意
I like your hat. It's original ...
年轻姑娘戴男士帽
a man's hat on a young girl.
而且您长得漂亮
And you're pretty.
可以为所欲为
You can do anything you like.
你是谁啊？
You're who?
我住在永隆
I live in Vinh Long.
永隆什么地方？
Where in Vinh Long?
就在河边上  那所带平台的大房子
On the river just outside. The big house with the terraces.
那个绿石头的？
The blue stone one?
对
Yes.
那是中国人的房子
It's a Chinese house.
我是中国人
I am Chinese.
中国人
Chinese.
他就是那伙儿搞金融的少数民族
He's from that financial minority ...
殖民地的所有房产业都是他们的
that owns all the popular housing of the colony.
他去过巴黎
He's back from Paris ...
在那儿学了点儿经商知识
where he undertook some business studies.
他就是那天渡河去西贡的人
He's the one who was crossing the Mekong that day towards Saigon
如果您需要 我可以开车送您去西贡
If you want, I can drive you to Saigon.
你认识她吗？
Do you know her?
她是总督的妻子
She's the administrator's wife ...
安妮-玛丽夫人
Mrs. Stretter, Anne-Marie.
您要尝一个吗？
Do you want one?
嗯 谢谢
Yes, thank you.
那个年轻人为了她自杀的故事
Is it true, that story about the young man ...
是真的吗？
who killed himself for her?
不清楚
Don't know.
是的  是真的
Yes, it's true.
就在琅勃拉邦的商业街上
On the marketplace at Louang Prabang ...
在她离去的那天
the day she left.
他是她的情人
He was her lover.
我抽烟您不介意吧？
The smoke doesn't bother you?
我是说 在车里
I mean, in here?
不  一点儿也不
No, not at all.
您在读西贡中学吧？
You're at Saigon High School?
是的  但是我不住校
Yes, but I sleep elsewhere ...
我在利奥泰学生宿舍寄宿
at the Lyautey Boardinghouse.
您喜欢学习吗？
Do you like studying?
是的  我觉得很有趣
Yes. I find it interesting.
您读几年级？
What grade are you in?
十一
11th.
那么您是
And you're ...
十七了
uh ...17.
你呢？
And you?
三十二了
32 ...
而且没有工作
and jobless.
而且是中国人  还有什么
And Chinese, what's more.
什么还有什么 ... 是的
What's more ...yes.
您说那句话的时候很美
You look so beautiful when you say that.
我母亲去世后 我父亲就没有下过床
Since my mother's death, my father has lived on his cot.
他离不开他的大烟枪 ...
He never leaves his opium pipe ...
而且他几乎什么都不吃
and he nearly doesn't eat anymore.
我始终猜不透他们的感情有多深
I never guessed the depth of their fondness.
这10年里
There it's been 10 years ...
他都是那样打理他的生意 ...
that's he's taken care of his business like that ...
在他的床上
from his bed.
他盯着河水看 您懂吧
He stares at the river, you see.
我懂
I see.
而且 我想念巴黎
Yes, I miss Paris ...
那些派对
the parties,
蒙巴纳斯的那些夜晚 ...
the evenings in Montparnasse ...
Coupole 穹顶餐厅
the coupole.
您知道 Coupole 吗？
Do you know the coupole?
我去过一次巴黎
I went to France once.
是在北边 靠近比利时边界
It was in the north, near the Belgian border.
我只知道这里 － 湄公河 西贡
I only know here-- the Mekong, Saigon.
您喜欢西贡吗？
You like Saigon?
是的 我喜欢西贡
Yes, I like Saigon.
我也喜欢西贡  尤其喜欢堤岸
I like Saigon, too. Cholon above all.
堤岸  就象是中国
Cholon, it's like China.
行了  我到了
That's it. It's here.
再见
Goodbye.
利奥泰学生宿舍
你这次回来得早
You got here earlier than usual.
我在渡船上遇到一个人  他开车送我来的
I met someone on the ferry. He drove me here.
一个中国人
A Chinaman.
海伦和我是宿舍里唯一的白人姑娘
Helene is the only other white girl in the boardinghouse.
是个完全不知害羞的姑娘
Helene, she is immodest.
她自己并没有意识到这一点
She doesn't realize.
她在宿舍一丝不挂走来走去
She walks naked in the dormitory.
她不知道自己非常美
She doesn't know that she's very beautiful.
她单纯无邪 ...
She's innocent ...
徜徉在豆蔻年华
lingering on in youth.
我忘了告诉你一件事
Hey, I forgot to tell you something.
有一个姑娘 被副舍监发现 ...
There's a girl ...the assistant mistresses found her ...
每天晚上出去卖淫 ...
she was a prostitute every evening ...
就在墙后面  谁都没有发现
behind the wall. Nobody noticed anything.
-是谁啊？ -爱丽丝
-Who? -Alice.
爱丽丝？她跟谁去做那种事啊？
Alice? Who's she going with like that?
任何人 ... 过路的
Anybody, people walking by.
我一直非常想
It's always appealed to me.
什么？
What?
跟不认识的男人走
To go with men you don't know.
你甚至看不见他们  什么都不知道
You don't even see them. Nothing.
永远都不知道他们长什么样
You'll never know their face.
你觉得我们都是那样的？
Do you think we're all like that?
是的  副舍监也是
Yes. The assistant mistresses, too.
每一个女人
Every woman.
实际上 我宁可做一个妓女 ...
Actually, I'd rather be a prostitute ...
也不愿意去护理麻风病人
than take care of lepers.
你又在说什么哪？
What are you talking about again?
学生们都这么说
That's what everybody says here.
大人们说我们要好好学习
They say they want us to study ...
其实不是这样
but it's not true.
她们让我们寄宿 ...
They take us into boarding ...
好把我们送到传染病医院去 ...
so they can send us to the lazarets ...
照顾那些麻风病人 瘟疫病人 疟疾病人
with the lepers, the plague-stricken, the cholera-ridden.
我宁可做一个妓女
I'd rather be a prostitute.
那他们走运了 － 那些男人们
They'd be lucky, those men.
利奥泰学生宿舍
越南法国国立中学
我是斗牛士  你是牛
I'm the matador. You are the bull.
目光平视  肩膀挺直
Eyes on one level. Shoulders straight.
一
1 ...
二
2 ...
三...四...
3 ...4 ...
五...六...
5 ...6.
从我的左肩望过去
Look over my left shoulder ...
回退  握臂  收臀
back out, arms locked, bottom in.
一二三四
And 1 and 2 and 3 and 4 ...
五六七八
and 5 and 6 and 7 and 8.
一二三四
And 1 and 2 and 3 and 4.
五六七八
5, 6, 7, 8.
那天是周四 是个假日  事情进展得很快
It happened very quickly that day, a holiday, a Thursday.
他是下午来的
He came that Thursday afternoon ...
直接来到学生宿舍
to the boardinghouse.
在一部黑色的大轿车里等她
He came to wait for her with the big black car.
中午刚过
It's early in the afternoon ...
是当地人睡午觉的时间
the time of the siesta.
他们去了堤岸
It's in Cholon ...
进了堤岸的小巷
in the alleyways of Cholon ...
四周弥漫着肉汤和烤肉的气味
in the smell of soup, roast meat ...
还有茉莉 尘土 炭火的气味 ...
jasmine, dust, charcoal fire ...
典型的唐人街气味
in the smell of the Chinese town.
请进
Please.
家具不是我选的
I ...l didn't choose the furniture.
是 ... 都是我父亲给我买的
It's--it's my father, bought me this.
年轻有钱的中国人 都包养情妇
Young, rich Chinese have mistresses ...
他们称这种地方为单身屋
and they call this the bachelor's room.
你有很多情妇吗
Do you have many mistresses?
你愿意我有情妇吗？
Do you like the idea of me having mistresses?
是的 我愿意
Yes, I do.
这么说 你可以跟我来这里
So you followed me here ...
也可以跟随便什么人来这里
as you would have followed anyone.
我不想知道
I wouldn't know.
我还从来没有跟任何人到一个屋子里去
I've never followed anyone into a room yet.
我 ... 我恐怕 ...
I'm ...I'm afraid ...
恐怕爱上你了
I'm afraid of loving you.
听我说 我们走吧  以后再找时间来
Listen, we'll leave. We'll come back some other time.
我宁愿你不爱我
Well, I'd rather you didn't love me.
我想做你平时和别的女人做的事情
I want you to do as you usually do with other women.
那是你想要的？
Is that what you want?
是的
Yes.
我知道你永远都不会爱我
I know you'll never love me.
我 ...
I ...
我不知道
I don't know.
我不想你讲话
I don't want you to talk.
象你平时那样做就行了
Just do as usual.
他扯去那条裙子
He tore the dress off.
扯去那条白色的小内裤
He tore the little white underpants off ...
然后把一丝不挂的她抱到床上
and he carried her like that ... naked, to the bed.
到了床上
Once on the bed ...
他却被恐惧所压倒
fear overcomes him.
我不能
I can't.
他说那不是真的 ...
He says it's not true ...
说她还太小 ...
that she's too little ...
说他不能做这种事
that he can't do such a thing.
于是 ...
So ...
她成为主动的一方
So she's the one who does it.
她合上双目 ...
Her eyes closed ...
给他脱衣服 ...
she undresses him ...
一个扣子一个扣子
button by button ...
一条袖子一条袖子
sleeve by sleeve.
这皮肤
The skin.
这滑软如丝的皮肤
The skin is of a sumptuous softness.
这没有体毛的身子
The body is hairless ...
完全没有任何雄性之强悍 ...
without any virility at all ...
除了性的部分
other than that of the sex.
她不正视他的面孔
She doesn't look him in the face.
触摸他的身体
She touches him.
她触摸柔软的性区 ...
She touches the softness of the sex ...
柔软的皮肤
of the skin.
她爱抚那金黄的色泽 ...
She caresses the golden hue ...
那未知的新奇部位
the unknown novelty.
那个寒酸简陋的地方 我至今历历在目
I still see the place of distress ...
象水底的沉船 ...
shipwrecked ...
四壁斑驳 ...
the distempered walls ...
被炉火熏黑的百叶窗
the slatted shutters giving up to the furnace.
血迹斑斑的床单
The soiling of the blood.
我记忆犹新
I remember well.
那个屋子非常阴暗
The room is dark.
外面喧闹声不绝于耳 ...
It's surrounded by the never-ending clamor of the town ...
屋里的人仿佛掉入车水马龙的漩涡之中
carried away by the town, by the flow of the town.
在那片噪音之中 ...
My body was in that public noise ...
在门口的路人面前 我的裸体一览无遗
this passing by from the outside ... exposed.
象是人的海洋  我心里想 ...
The sea, I thought ...
铺天盖地
the immensity.
你在想什么？
What are you thinking about?
他们死了
They're dead.
疼吗？
Did it hurt you?
不
No.
你很难过吗？
Are you sad?
是的 大概吧
Yes, I guess.
有一点儿
A little.
我不知道
I don't know.
那是因为我们在白天做爱 ...
It's because we've made love during the daytime ...
而且天气非常炎热
in the dead of the heat.
不是
No.
是因为我
It's me.
我总是有一点儿难过
I'm always a little sad.
就象我妈妈一样
I'm like my mother.
我告诉她我希望当一个作家
When I told her I'd be a writer ...
她耸耸肩膀
she shrugged.
她说那样不行 ...
She said it's not work ...
说那个想法很幼稚
it's a childish idea.
她要我学数学 我妈妈教数学 ...
She wants me to do maths, my mother does ...
好去挣钱
to earn money.
你想写什么呢？
What do you want to write?
写书
Books.
写小说
Novels ...
写我的哥哥
about my elder brother ...
把他杀了 ...
to kill him ...
看他受苦 ...
to see him in pain ...
让他死
to make him die.
写我的弟弟 救他
About my younger brother to save him.
还写 ...
And about that--
写我妈妈的难过
about my mother's sadness.
写她如何缺钱  写她的羞耻
About the lack of money, about shame.
我知道你妈妈运气很糟糕 ...
I know the bad luck with your mother ...
知道她经历的悲剧
and the tragedies she's lived.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
我的佣人说的
Through the servants.
还有我的司机
Through my driver.
通过佣人 你什么都能知道
You know everything through the servants.
我也知道你哥哥
I know about your elder brother, too.
我在河边的烟馆见过他
I met him in the opium dens along the riverside.
他烟瘾很大
He smokes too much.
简直太大了
Much too much.
白人不懂怎么吸大烟
The whites don't know how to smoke.
他不是人
He's an animal.
他让我害怕
He scares me.
他偷妈妈的钱去吸鸦片
He steals from my mother to go smoke.
他还偷佣人的钱
He steals from the servants.
妈妈始终不吭声
My mother never says anything.
妈妈最爱他
He's her favorite.
父亲死后 家里没钱了
Since my father died, there's no money in the house.
妈妈把什么都赔光了
My mother lost everything here.
她的所有选择都是错的
She made all the wrong choices.
那你们怎么办？
So how do you manage?
我们只能尽力而为
We do the best we can.
我们顾不上羞耻
We're shameless.
只能尽力而为
We do the best we can.
你来这里 是因为我有钱吗？
Did you come here because I've got money?
我不知道
I don't know.
我来是因为我喜欢你
I came because I liked you.
如果我是穷人 你还喜欢我吗？
Would you like me if I were poor?
我喜欢现在的你
I like you the way you are ...
有钱的你
with your money.
我想带你走
I want to take you away.
我愿意带你走 ...
I'd like to take you away ...
和你一起生活
live with you.
我现在还不能离开妈妈
I can't leave without my mother yet.
我还太小
I'm too little.
我不能离开妈妈和弟弟  现在还不能
I can't leave my mother nor my little brother. Not yet.
我要他一次又一次地做
I had asked him to do it again and again.
为我做
To do it to me.
他做了
He had done it.
他在血泊中做
He had done it in the unctuousness of blood.
我认为他对此习以为常
I think he's used to it.
那就是他的生活 －
This is what he does in life--
爱  别的都不操心
Love. Nothing else.
我非常幸运
I'm very lucky.
那好像是他的职业
Obviously, it's as if it were a profession he'd have.
他在我上面 ...
He's on me ...
他又一次爆发
he engulfs himself again.
我们就那样守在一起  合为一体 ...
We stay like that, nailed ...
在街头的喧闹声中呻吟
moaning in the clamor of the town.
你知道吗
You see ...
这个下午会让你终生难忘 ...
you'll remember this afternoon all your life ...
即便你忘了我的相貌 ...
even if you've forgotten my face ...
我的名字
my name.
你说我会记得这个屋子吗？
Do you think I'll remember the room?
好好看看它
Take a good look at it.
和别的地方一样
It's like anywhere.
这就对了
That's it.
永远不会变
It's like always.
我搞不懂是什么力量 ...
I wonder how I found the strength ...
让我能如此平静 ...
the forbidden with this calm ...
如此坚决地偷吃禁果
this determination ...
我又是如何成功地 ...
how I succeeded in going all the way ...
完全实现了我的荒诞念头
to the end of the idea.
如何独自一人 从这个陌生男人那里 ...
How could I have taken so much pleasure ...
获得如此之大的快乐？
for me alone with this unknown man?
我妈妈 ...
My mother ...
她要是知道了这件事 会杀了我
she'll kill me if she finds out the truth.
我哥哥 ... 他会杀了你
My brother, he'd kill you.
无法想像 ...
Imagine ...
和一个中国人
with a Chinaman.
从我很小起 ...
Since I've been little ...
妈妈就告诉我在殖民地 ...
she tells me that here in the colonies ...
一个姑娘如果不是处女了 ...
a girl that isn't a virgin anymore ...
就再也找不到丈夫了
can no longer find a husband.
你说 真的是这样吗？
Do you think that's true?
是的  你母亲没有说错
Yes. Your mother's right.
如果发生了那种 ... 丢人的事情
It's no longer possible after that--
就不可能了
that dishonor.
比如说 ...
For instance ...
如果我想娶你 ...
if I wanted to marry you ...
这将是不允许的
well, it would not be allowed.
我们绝不能容忍这样的想法
We can't tolerate the idea of that.
我是中国人
I'm Chinese.
对不起
I'm sorry.
既然你已经和我做了那种事
Now that you've done that with me ...
我们之间就不可能结婚了
marriage between us would be impossible.
这样啊 ... 那再好不过了
Well, then, it's for the best, then.
中国人 － 我不怎么喜欢中国人
Chinese--I don't like Chinese very much.
嘿
Hey.
我可以到你床上去吗？
Can I come into your bed?
不行  现在不要
No, not now.
我明天再告诉你
I'll tell you about it tomorrow.
是怎么了？出什么事了？
What's wrong? What's the matter?
越南法国国立中学
她为什么上那部新轿车啊？
What's she doing in that new car there?
您好
Hello.
等等 等等
Wait. Wait.
不用难为情  成绩非常好
Don't be bashful. It's a wonderful report.
她是唯一继承人 我也是
She's the sole heiress, and I'm the sole heir.
好多年前就定下日子了
The date has been set for years.
这是我从法国回来的另一个原因
That's another reason I came back from France.
你爱她吗？
You love her?
不爱
No.
我不认识她
I don't know her.
对我们来说 ...
For us ...
婚姻都是家族包办的
marriages are arranged by the families.
我们知道今后一起生活是无法想像的
We know that a future together is unthinkable ...
所以我们以漫不经心的口吻谈论未来
so we speak of the future in a casual manner ...
不牵扯丝毫私人情感
without any involvement, detached.
两个家族搞到一起 ...
And the two families got together ...
把他们的财富藏起来
to hide their wealth away.
这是中国重要的风俗 ...
It's so much the customs of ancient ...
不管是古代还是现代中国
or modern China.
我们没有任何其它选择
We don't think we could do anything any other way.
他从来没有过工作
He's never had a job.
他说如果他是穷人 ...
He says that if he was poor ...
那就太可怕了
it would be terrible.
他太懒了 不会去工作
He'd be much too lazy to work.
是鸦片让人没有了力气
It's opium that takes away the strength.
不
No.
是他的财富让他没有了力气
It's wealth that takes his strength away.
他什么都不做
He does nothing.
什么都不做
Nothing.
就知道爱
Only love.
不过好笑的是
But it's funny ...
我就因为这个才想要他
because that's the way I desire him.
你还爱我吗？
Do you still love me?
我们是情人
We are lovers.
我们每天回到那个单身屋
Every day we go back to the bachelor's room.
我们无法停止相爱
We can't stop loving.
我们每天傍晚 都来堤岸的这个脏兮兮的街区幽会
This takes place in the sleazy district of Cholon every evening.
每天傍晚 ...
Every evening ...
这个少女来享受快乐 ...
the little one comes to receive the pleasure ...
也让这个皮肤黝黑的男人叫出声来
that makes one scream from this dark man ...
堤岸的这个中国男人 ...
this man from Cholon ... from China.
沙 沥 小 学
嘿 妈妈
Hi, Mom.
嘿 保罗
Hi, Paul.
我不时回到沙沥 ...
Now and then I go back to the house in Sa-Dec ...
回到那个恐怖的家
to the horror of the house in Sa-Dec.
那是一个无法忍受地方
It's an unbearable place.
在死亡的阴影下 ...
It's close to death ...
充满暴力 痛苦 绝望 和无耻
a place of violence, of pain, of despair, of dishonor.
禁止你摔门！听见没有？
I forbid you to slam doors! Do you hear me?
谁开车送你回来的？
Who drove you back from Saigon?
我告诉过你  是个朋友  住永隆
I told you. A friend. He lives in Vinh Long.
他正好顺路 所以主动提出送我
He offered to drop me off on his way through.
是个朋友  不过如此！
He's a friend! That's all.
谁住永隆啊？
Who in Vinh Long?
你不认识
You wouldn't know him.
他刚才巴黎回来
He just got back from Paris.
是个朋友  有钱的朋友
A friend. A rich friend.
不是每个人都有幸做穷人的
Not everybody's lucky enough to be poor.
那么这个 ...
And this ...
这是什么？
what's this?
一张蓝纸
A piece of blue paper.
是学生宿舍发的电报
It's a telegram from the boardinghouse.
周二和周三你在什么地方过夜？
Where did you sleep Tuesday and Wednesday?
周二和周三我在什么地方过夜？
Where did I sleep Tuesday and Wednesday?
没在宿舍
Not at the boardinghouse.
风扇坏了
The fans were out of order.
我跟永隆的朋友睡觉了
I slept with my friend from Vinh Long.
这就是你要我说的？
Is that what you want me to say?
揍她  妈妈
Hit her, Mom.
别让她躲过去
Don't let her get away with it.
然而 正是这个家庭的冷漠 ...
But it's in this family's dryness ...
和极度的严酷
in its incredible harshness ...
让我深信不疑地确定 ...
that I am the most deeply assured of myself in the deepest of my essential certainties ...
我们一家的毁灭和羞耻 ...
Our common history of ruin and shame ...
爱与恨 根源正是我的肉身
of love and hate, is in my flesh.
您的女儿像个婊子
Your daughter looks like a whore.
嗨 你个傻瓜  别打了！
Hey, dummy, stop that shooting!
我还待在这个家里
I am still in this family.
也就是说 拒绝去所有其它住处
This is, barring all other places where I live.
那是你的裙子 妈妈
That was your dress, Mom.
鞋子也是你给我买的 我穿了几个月了
The shoes, you bought them for me. I've been wearing them for months.
记得吗？大减价的时候
They were on sale, remember? Final reductions.
你是故意这样
You do it on purpose.
没看见我因为你落到什么地步了？
See what a state I'm in because of you?
好象这能让你开心似的
It's as though it makes you happy.
要是你不再信任我 ...
If you don't trust me anymore ...
索性让我离开宿舍好了
just take me out of the boardinghouse.
再说 并不是我自己要独自一个人 ...
Besides, I'm not the one who asked to be all alone ...
整年待在西贡的
all year long in Saigon.
母亲有时候会非常非常开心 ...
The mother can be very, very happy sometimes ...
忘记一切烦恼
the time to forget.
单是全家打扫卫生 就能让妈妈开心起来
That of washing the house may suffice for my mother's happiness.
她弹钢琴 搞卫生 欢笑 ...
She plays the piano, she cleans, she laughs ...
每个人都以为 ...
and everyone thinks ...
这所破房子 突然变成沼泽 ...
that one can be happy in this gutted house that suddenly becomes a swamp ...
变成河边的田地 变成渡口 沙滩
a field alongside a river ...
就能让人开心起来
a ford, a beach.
至为荣幸 夫人
My respects, madame.
我母亲
My mother ...
我哥哥皮埃尔
my brother Pierre ...
我弟弟保罗
and my brother Paul.
周六晚上 这里比较热闹
On Saturday night they are busy.
来份鸡尾酒吗 先生？
Will you be having a cocktail, sir?
是的  三杯马耳特-百悦  一瓶米酒
Yes. Three Martel-Perriers and a bottle of rice wine.
孙中山建立共和国后 我们离开了中国 ...
We left China when Sun Yat-sen decreed the republic ...
家父把他的地都卖给日本人 ...
and my father just sold all his lands to the Japanese ...
后者已经占领了满洲里
who had already taken over Manchuria--
还卖掉了所有房子 珠宝  都卖了 ...
all the houses, jewels, and everything ...
然后去了南方
to go down towards the south.
我母亲 ...
And my mother ...
她病倒在路上 ...
she'd just lie in the road ...
再也走不动了 ...
and she can't go on anymore ...
母亲和两个兄弟一定什么都没有听见
The mother and the brothers mustn't know a thing.
我们已经原则上说好：
It is set by principle ...
他是跪着求我 ...
that he's at my feet ...
我和他在一起是为了钱 ...
that I'm with him for the money ...
我不能爱他
that I can't love him.
因为他是中国人  因为他不是白人
This because he's Chinese, because he's not white.
我的两个兄弟狼吞虎咽 根本不理睬他
My brothers devour and don't speak a word to him.
我也不理他
I don't speak a word to him, either.
在家人面前 他不再是我的情人
In my family's presence, he ceases to be my lover.
他依旧存在 ...
He doesn't cease to exist ...
但在我眼里已无足轻重
but he's nothing to me anymore.
他成了没有地位的人 ...
He becomes a burned-out place ...
成为无法接受的丑闻 ...
an unacceptable scandal ...
成为羞耻的原因 必须予以隐藏
a reason to be ashamed of, that has to be hidden.
那么 我们在等什么？
So, what are we waiting for?
我希望去水帘舞厅喝一杯
I'd like to have a drink at La Cascade.
您的账单 先生
Your bill, sir.
我们希望去水帘舞厅喝酒和跳舞 ...
We'd like to go to La Cascade to drink and dance.
你笑什么 ...
What makes you laugh ...
因为我跟你妹妹跳舞？
that I'm dancing with your sister?
不好意思
I'm sorry.
你俩太不配了
You're so badly paired.
别理他 先生
Don't pay attention, sir.
他醉了 不过如此
He's drunk, that's all.
什么？
What?
我不能笑还是怎么着？
Can't I laugh or what?
你想打架吗？
Do you want to fight?
小心点儿 小朋友
Take care, little buddy.
我让你这样的两个
It'd take two of you to do the job.
不
Oh, no.
远不止两个
A lot more than that.
要四个我
Four of me, you mean.
你想不出我多不禁打
You have no idea how weak I am.
我们该走了
We should leave.
原谅他 先生
Forgive him, sir.
原谅我们
Forgive us.
我教子无方
I've not brought my children up well.
正在付出代价
I'm paying for it.
我已经受到最大的惩罚
I'm the one who's punished the most.
我们刚才做的值多少？
How much is what we did worth?
在妓院里 你象刚才那样做 ...
In a brothel, how much does it cost ...
要花多少钱？
to do what you just did to me?
你需要多少？
How much do you need?
我妈妈需要 500 比索
My mother needs 500 piasters.
我拿到钱了
I've got your money.
这里
Here.
她办公室在哪儿？
Where's her office?
就在那边
It's over there.
您知道 我们需要让她晚上自由活动
You see, we have to let her go free in the evening ...
不要规定她几点回宿舍
not tell her what time to be in.
我们也千万不能强迫她和同学们一起去游玩
We mustn't force her to go on trips with the boarders, either.
她一直是个不受拘束的孩子  要是不这样 她会出走的
She's always been a free child. Otherwise, she'd run away.
就连我都不敢强迫她
Even I can't do a thing about that.
即便没有人管束 她也一直用功学习
She's always worked very well in school even being so free.
舍监同意了 因为我是白人 ...
The headmistress accepted because I'm white ...
而且为了学生宿舍的声誉 ...
and that for the boardinghouse's reputation ...
在所有这些混血的孩子中 必须有几个白人
amongst all the half-castes there must be a few whites.
她允许我在宿舍象住旅店一样
She let me live in the boardinghouse as if it were a hotel.
除了我的法文老师 ...
Other than my French teacher ...
学校里没有人跟我讲话
nobody speaks to me at school.
都是因为你
It's because of you.
那是你的想象
That's your imagination.
不
No.
有些家长已经投诉了
There have been some complaints from families.
他们说我是个荡妇 ...
They say I'm a slut ...
到贫民区去 ...
and goes to the shady part of town ...
让一个中国人摸她的身子
to have her body fondled by a Chinaman.
没关系的
It's nothing.
的确 是没关系
That's true. It's nothing.
哎呀！球碰到她了  真恶心
Ooh! It touched her. It's nasty.
哎呀！她和一个中国人睡觉
Ooh! She sleeps with a Chinaman.
你早晚要回法国的
One day you're going to go back to France.
我简直无法接受
I can't take that.
你什么时候回法国？
When are you going back to France?
毕业以后 ...
At the end of the school year ...
但是还没有定
but it's not sure.
妈妈还有很多麻烦 无法离开这里
My mother has a lot of difficulty in leaving here.
这块宝石是我母亲的
The stone belonged to my mother.
拿去吧
Take it.
老爷
阿爹
我今天回来看你
我想你已经知道 我结识了一个法国女子
我承认
我经常跟这个法国女子待在一起
我真的不可以离开这个法国女子
我真的很爱她
一年啊
请阿爹你 准许我们正式结婚
一年之后我们再做打算
好不好阿爹
不可以答应你
十年来
我已经安排好你的婚事
我同女方已经定好良辰吉日
谁的话都不好使
爹
行了行了
而且我跟他说我们的爱刚刚开始 ...
And I said to him that it's too new ...
非常强烈 ...
it's too strong ...
我还跟他说 ...
and I said to him that ...
拆散我们是非常残酷的
it is horrid to take you away from my body.
我跟他说 ...
I--I said to him that he--my father--
他 － 我父亲 应该懂得这种爱 ...
he--he should know what it is ...
这样强烈的爱 ...
a love like this-- so strong ...
一人生中不会再有第二次
that it never happens again in a lifetime--
永远不会
never.
他要我跟这个年轻姑娘结婚 ...
He wants this marriage with ...
我从来都没有见过她
this young girl I've never seen.
他一点儿也不同情我
He shows no mercy for me.
他不同情任何人
He shows none for anyone.
那么你呢？
And you?
你想不想和她结婚？
Do you want this marriage?
问题不是我想不想
The question is not of wanting or not wanting.
没有我父亲的财富 我什么都不是
I'm nothing without my father's wealth.
他对我说 ...
He told me ...
“我宁可看到你死 ...”
"I'd rather see you dead ...
“也不想看到你跟那个白人姑娘在一起”
than know you were with that white girl."
但是他说的对啊
But he's right.
因为我早晚是要离去的 ...
He's right because anyhow I'll leave ...
再说我也不爱你
and I have no love for you.
你看
You see.
就是这里
It's here.
我小时候 ...
My mother, when I was little ...
妈妈想在这里建一个水坝 来保护她的良田
wanted to erect a dam to protect her good-growing land.
为了我们 她想变得富有
She wanted to become rich for us.
她把父亲死后留下的全部积蓄都投了进去
She put all the savings left after my father's death into it.
她被人骗了
People lied to her.
地被淹后  土地管理局的代理卖了地 ...
The land registrar agents sold her flood lands ...
好从中提成
just to earn their premiums.
海水把什么都淹了
Saltwater covered everything.
她丧失了这里的一切 － 所有的东西
She lost everything here--everything.
她用了好几年的时间 才相信人们会偷走她的全部积蓄 ...
It took her years to believe that it was possible for people to steal all her savings ...
然后再也不承认她 还把她赶出去
and then never acknowledge her again, to throw her out.
她一次次发作
She would scream. She had fits.
人们开始说她疯了 ...
People started to say that she was crazy ...
再也不相信她说的 关于她的钱的事情 ...
to not believe what she said about her money anymore ...
人们说她撒谎
to say that she was lying.
我们好多年没有和白人来往
We never saw another white person for years.
白种人都以我们为耻
The whites were ashamed of us.
她不得不放弃一切
She had to give everything up.
她把高处的稻田送给了佣人
The upper rice paddy -- she gave it to the servants ...
还有房子和所有的家具
along with the bungalow and all the furniture.
我们常常坐在这里 ...
We used to sit here ...
我和妈妈还有弟弟 ...
with my mother and my little brother ...
望着山那边 泰国的天空
and we'd watch the sky of Siam over there behind the mountains.
你冷吗？
You feel cold?
有一点儿
A little.
就在那个傍晚 我知道了我要做的事情
That evening I know it.
而且是我唯一要做的事情
I know only that ...
以后我要写妈妈的生活
later I will write my mother's life--
写土地管理局的代理如何毁了她 ...
how she was killed by the land registrar agents ...
政府官员如何趁火打劫
robbed by the government officials.
我要写作 －
To write--
那是我所看到的未来 ...
that's what I see beyond the moment ...
在那片荒地上 ...
in that great desert ...
在落日的余晖中 ...
under the features of which ...
我看到了我未来的人生
I see the extent of my life.
她美吗？
Is she beautiful?
她很有钱
She's rich.
家里选择她 也是因为她有钱
The family chose her also because of that.
她的衣服上有金子 ...
She's covered with gold ...
翡翠 ...
jade ...
还有钻石
and diamonds.
在我之前 你和白人姑娘睡过吗？
Did you ever sleep with a white girl before me?
在巴黎 当然
In Paris, of course.
在这里 没有
Here, no.
为什么？
Why?
在这里 ...
Here ...
除了法国妓女 ...
other than French prostitutes ...
不可能和白种女人来往
it's impossible to have white women.
完全不可能
Totally impossible.
我要你亲口对我说一遍
I want you to say it to me once.
你来是为了得到我的钱
You came here so that I'd give you money.
我来是为了得到你的钱
I came here so that you'd give me money.
跟着我说
Repeat after me.
从我在渡船上看到你那一刻起 ...
I was thinking about money ...
我想的就是钱 ...
and only about money ...
仅仅是钱
from the moment I saw you on the ferry.
从我在渡船上看到你那一刻起 ...
I was thinking about money ...
我想的就是钱 ...
and only about money ...
仅仅是钱
since the moment I saw you on the ferry.
你是个婊子
You're a whore.
我没有感觉恶心
I don't find that disgusting.
正相反 ...
On the contrary ...
你知道 ...
You know ...
在你之前 ...
before you ...
我完全不知道什么是痛苦
I knew nothing about suffering.
我非常想 ...
I would love to ...
我非常想带你走 ...
I would love to take you ...
但是我没有力量
but I'm without strength.
我完全没有任何力量
I'm without any strength at all.
我死了
I'm dead.
我对你没有欲望
I have no desire for you.
我的身体不再想要不爱自己的人
My body no longer wants the one who doesn't love.
你知道这值多少钱吗？
Do you know what that's worth?
你要我们相信 ...
You want to have us believe ...
他给你这个 仅仅是为了你的漂亮脸蛋？
he just gave it to you for your pretty face?
他为什么给你这么大的钻石？
Why did he give you such a diamond?
为什么？因为他很有钱
Why? Because he's rich.
你的女儿在卖身
Your daughter's whoring.
拿去好了！卖了它！
Take it! Sell it!
看我在乎不在乎这个戒指！
See if I care about that ring!
你和他睡了  我敢肯定
You slept with him. I'm sure of it.
一看就知道
Just take a look at her.
她太不知羞耻了
She's a disgrace.
什么
What?
你一定要收拾她  妈
You've got to do something, Mum.
你们说什么哪？我 和一个中国人？
What are you saying? Me with a Chinaman?
什么都没有发生 － 什么都没有 ...
Nothing happened-- nothing--
连接吻都没有
not even a kiss.
有中国人的气味
It smells of Chinese.
他跟你睡了
He slept with you.
承认吧
Say it.
给我承认！
Say it!
你必须承认 你个婊子
You're going to say it, you bitch!
你个肮脏的婊子
You filthy bitch!
你跟中国佬睡觉  你很喜欢对不对？
You slept with a Chink. Did you like it? Huh?
皮埃尔 住手！
Pierre, stop!
住手 给我住手！你快弄死她了！
Stop it, I say! Stop it! You're going to kill her!
住手！住手 看上帝份上！
Stop it! Stop it, for god's sake!
你快弄死她了 皮埃尔！
You're killing her, Pierre!
住手！
Stop it!
我还以为我的孩子不会来了
I thought my child wouldn't come anymore.
我叫了一辆人力车
I took a rickshaw.
你吸了很多吗？
Did you smoke a lot?
这是我唯一的事情
That's all I do.
我没有了欲望
I have no desire left.
我没有了爱
I have no love left.
真太奇妙了
It's wonderful.
就好象我们从来没有见过 ...
It's as though we'd never met ...
或者你离去了好几个月
or as though you left months ago.
你什么时候结婚？
When are you getting married?
下周五
Next Friday ...
然后离开这里 ...
and leaving ...
乘亚历山杜马号轮船
on the Alexandre Dumas the 12th.
看着我
Look at me.
我早晚会因为爱你而死
I'm going to die of love for you.
你结婚后 ...
After your marriage ...
我们在这里见面 ...
we'll meet here one time--
就一次
just once.
记住了吗？
You remember?
你答应我
You promise d me.
那个红木桌也要卖吗？
You're also selling the rosewood table?
是的
Yes.
所有的东西都留下
I'm leaving everything.
这里的一切都结束了
It's all finished here.
我唯一舍不得的 是哪些铁床
The only thing I'll miss are the metal beds.
法国的床太软
In France, the beds are too soft.
那帽子怎么回事？
What's that hat?
妈妈 我戴了好几个月了
Mom, I've been wearing it for months.
是我给你买的吗？
-Did I buy that for you?
还能有谁？
Who else?
总有一天 我们可以让你买我们喜欢的任何东西
Some days we can make you buy anything we want.
我都忘了
I forgot.
你知道 ...
You know ...
我和你不一样
I wasn't like you.
我学东西没有你那么容易 ...
I didn't study as easily as you do ...
而且我 ...
and l ...
我非常认真 ...
I was very serious ...
认真了这么久 － 太久了
for so long--too long.
所以我已经感觉不到自己的快乐
That's how I lost the feeling of my own pleasure.
他的确做了一件好事 真的
He did a really good thing, truly.
谁做了一件好事？
Who did a good thing?
你的朋友 －
Your friend--
你的中国朋友
your Chinese friend.
他替你哥还清了烟馆的债
He paid off your brother's debts at the opium den.
还付了路费
He also paid for the trip.
他真了不起 －
He was wonderful--
也非常谨慎
very discreet, too.
我过去低估了他
I had underestimated him.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry about that.
你是单纯为钱 才和他在一起吗？
Do you only see him for the money?
是的
Yes.
当第一遍发船汽笛声响起
It was when the boat uttered its first farewell ...
舷梯吊起来 ...
and the gangway had been hauled up ...
拖船开始出发 ...
and the tugs had started to tow it ...
将轮船拖离码头的时候 ...
to draw it away from the land ...
她哭了
that she had wept.
她强忍住泪水
She'd done it without showing her tears ...
不让妈妈和弟弟看见她的悲伤 ...
without showing her mother or her little brother that she was sad ...
什么都不流露出来 ...
without showing anything ...
就象家里的惯例一样
as was the custom between them.
他在那儿
He was there.
那是他  在远处 －
That was him in the back--
几乎看不见 ...
that scarcely visible shape ...
他一动不动  身心崩溃
that made no movement, crushed.
她俯在栏杆上 ...
She was leaning on the railing ...
象渡船初见那天一样
like the first time on the ferry.
她知道他在望着她
She knew he was watching her.
她也望着他
She was watching him, too.
她已经看不到他了
She couldn't see him anymore, but she still looked ...
但是仍然朝那辆黑色的轿车望去
towards the shape of the black car.
直到它消失在视野中
In the end, she didn't see it anymore.
码头也渐渐消失 ...
The harbor had faded away ...
接着是陆地
and then the land.
一天夜里 轮船穿越印度洋时
One night, during the crossing of the Indian Ocean ...
甲板上突然响起肖邦的圆舞曲
in the main room on the big deck there had been a sudden burst of a waltz by Chopin.
海上寂静无风 ...
There wasn't a breath of wind ...
于是在那个夜晚 ...
and that night ...
音乐回荡整个邮轮 ...
the music had spread all over the black liner ...
犹如天籁 ...
Like an injunction from heaven ...
关乎未知 ...
related to something unknown ...
象是上帝的指令 ...
Like an order from God ...
其含义深奥莫测 ...
whose meaning was inscrutable.
她哭了 ...
She had wept ...
因为她想到堤岸的那个男人
because she had thought of that man from Cholon--
她的情人 －
her lover--
突然之间 她不再确定自己是不是从未爱过他 ...
and suddenly she wasn't sure of not having loved him ...
还是由于那是一种她从未见过的爱 ...
with a love she hadn't seen ...
消散在这个故事当中 ...
because it had lost itself in the story ...
如水入沙 ...
Like water in the sand ...
而现在 ... 在荡漾于海上的乐声中
and that she was rediscovering it now ...
她重新找到了这种爱
in this moment of music flung across the sea.
二战后 ...
Years after the war ...
在我成婚 养儿育女 ...
after the marriages, the children ...
然后又离婚 出书后 ...
the divorces, the books ...
他和妻子来到巴黎
he had come to Paris with his wife.
他打电话给她
He had phoned her.
他非常胆怯
He was intimidated.
声音颤抖 ...
His voice trembled ...
他的中国口音也在颤抖中再次出现
and with the trembling, it had found the accent of China again.
他知道她开始写书
He knew she'd begun writing books.
也得知她弟弟的死讯
He had also heard about the younger brother's death.
他为她难过 ...
He had been sad for her ...
接着 他不知道对她说什么好了 ...
and then he hadn't known what to tell her ...
然后 他对她说了
and then he'd told her--
以前也对她说过的话 －
he had told her that it was as before ...
他依然爱她 ...
that he still loved her ...
而且永远爱她 ...
that he would never stop loving her ...
至死不渝
that he would love her until his death.
翻译：舒杭生
北平℡英文翻译工作室
hsheng06@gmail.com